A Guide to the Warren County (Va.) Land Records, 1788-1937 (bulk 1836-1937)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Warren County (Va.) Land Records, 1788-1937 (bulk 1836-1937)
The Library of Virginia
1096484-1150052 circa
23 boxes and 11 v.
Warren County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in a shipment of court papers from Warren County.
Historical Information
Warren County was named for Joseph Warren, the revolutionary patriot who sent Paul Revere and William Dawes on their famous rides and who was killed at the Battle of Bunker Hill. The county was formed from Frederick and Shenandoah counties in 1836.
Deeds of bargain and sale are the most commonly recorded deed in which one individual sells property, usually land, but occasionally personal property, to another individual. Such deeds show the names of the grantor and grantee, the residence of both parties, a description of what is being sold, the consideration (or price), the location of the tract of land, the tract's boundaries, and any limitations on the property being sold. The deed was signed by the grantor, and possibly his wife or anyone else having a claim to the property, and by at least two witnesses. Appended to the deed may be a memorandum of livery of seisin, stating that the property has changed hands and that peaceful possession has taken place.
Deeds of gift are often found transferring property, either real or personal, from one individual to another "for love and affection." The degree of kinship, if any, between the grantor and grantee is sometimes stated.
Mortgages and deeds of trust were deeds where one party is indebted to another and transfers or mortgages property to a third party to secure the debt. Deeds of release were made by the trustees after payment of the debt, for the purpose of divesting themselves of the legal title and revesting it in the original owner.
Scope and Content
Warren County (Va.) Land Records, 1788-1937 (bulk 1836-1937) contains Index to Deeds, 1839-1901 circa, A-C; Index to Deeds, 1839-1901 circa, D-J; Index to Deeds, 1839-1901 circa, K-R; Index to Deeds, 1839-1901 circa, S-Z; General Index to Deeds,1839-1923; Records of Releases; List of Conveyances; List of Conveyances Posted Monthly; Conveyances Admitted to Record in the Clerk's Office of the Warren County Court; County Land Records; lose deeds from Deed Books A-D and Deed Books 15-42; Old Deeds-Bill of Sale Agreements; Plats and Surveys made by the county surveyor; Release Deeds; Plats; Grants; List of Grants; and four Deeds for land formerly in Shenandoah County.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Warren County Court Records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Warren County (Va.) Circuit Court
Subjects:
Deeds--Virginia--Warren County; Plats--1875-1927; Public Records--Virginia--Warren County
Geographical Names:
Warren County (Va.)--History
Genre and Form Terms:
Local government Records--Virginia--Warren County
Contents List
- List of Conveyances, 1863-1886 (bulk 1876-1886)
  Barcode Number 1096484 is List of Conveyances, 1863-1874. Barcode Number 1096577 is List of Conveyances Post Monthly, 1876-1882. Barcode Number 1096580 is List of Conveyances, 1882-1886.
- County Land Records, Volume A, 1842-1846
  This volume contains land records.
- Indexes to Deeds, A-Z, 1836-1901 circa
  Barcode Number 1096513 is Index to Deeds, A-C; Barcode 1096525 is Index to Deeds, D-J; Barcode Number 1096523 is Index to Deeds, K-R; and Barcode Number 1096511 is Index to Deeds, S-Z.
- Records of Release, Volume 1, 1884-1909
  This volume contains release deeds.
- General Index to Deeds, 1839-1923
  This volume is an inclusive deed index.
- Conveyances, 1836-1842
  These conveyances were admitted to record in the Clerk's Office of the Warren County Court.
- Deeds, 1836-1899
  These are copies of original deeds the clerk used to record the information into the Deed Books. On the back of the individual deeds, the Clerk recorded the letter of the Deed Book and the page on which the deed was recorded. Barcode Number 1141723 contains deeds recorded 1836-1850, Box 1. Barcode Number 1141724 contains deeds recorded 1851-1873, Box 2. Barcode Number 1141725 contains deeds recorded 1873-1886, Box 3. Barcode Number 1141726 contains deeds recorded 1886-1892, Box 4. Barcode Number 1141727 contains deeds recorded 1893-1899, Box 5.
- Deeds, 1899-1903
  Box 6 contains deeds numbered 102-1357.
- Deeds, 1903-1937
  On the back of the individual deeds, the Clerk recorded the number of the Deed Book and the page on which the deed was recorded. Barcode Number 1141729 contains deeds recorded June 1903-Aug. 1906, numbered 1358-2000, 4-237, and 242-482, Box 7. Barcode Number 1141730 contains deeds recorded Aug. 1906-Dec. 1909, Numbers 485-1776, Box 8. Barcode Number 1141731 contains deeds recorded Jan. 1910-Mar. 1912, Numbers 1785-2000 and 1-1079, Box 9. Barcode Number 1141732 contains deeds recorded Sept. 1912-Apr. 1915, Numbers 1086-828, Box 10. Barcode Number 1141733 contains deeds recorded Apr. 1915-Oct. 1917, Numbers 829-312, Box 11. Barcode Number 1141734 contains deed recorded Oct. 1917-Mar. 1919, Numbers 314-114, Box 12. Barcode Number 1141735 contains deeds recorded Mar. 1919-Mar. 1921, Numbers 175-89, Box 13. Barcode Number 1141736 contains deeds recorded Mar. 1921-May 1923, Numbers 92-137, Box 14. Barcode Number 1141737 contains deeds recorded Apr. 1923-Apr. 1926, Numbers 138-197, Box 15. Barcode Number 1141738 contains deeds recorded May 1926-Jul. 1930, Numbers 203-179, Box 16. Barcode Number 1141739 contains deeds recorded Aug. 1930-May 1937, Numbers 181-258, Box 17. Barcode Number 1141740 contains deeds recorded May 1937-Nov. 1937, Numbers 262-289, Box 18.
- Land Records, 1839-1899 (bulk 1839-1878)
  Box 19 contains Old Deeds; Bill of Sale agreements; Plats and Surveys made by county surveyor. The previously listed records are from the period 1839-1878. Other records are Release Deeds, 1884-1889, pages 1-180; and 1899, Number 272.
- Plats, 1875-1927
  Barcode 1141743, Oversize Box 1 contains Plats 1875-1927 and Barcode 1141744, Oversize Box 2 contains Plats 1890-1913.
- Grants, 1794-1877 (bulk 1875-1877)
  Oversize Box 4 contains a Grant issued in 1794 and a List of Grants issued Aug. 1875-May 1877.
- Deeds, 1788-1799 circa
  This oversized box contains 4 deeds that were for land formerly in Shenandoah County.